# Mark Smith-Guerrero

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

With over two decades of extensive and diverse experience, Mark is committed to elevating user experiences across multiple domains. He excels in comprehending and addressing the needs of end-users, administrators, and engineers, adeptly improving processes through innovative technological solutions.

U.S. Citizen (571) 228-8479 msmithgu@gmail.com github.com/msmithgu

# **KEY SKILLS AND QUALIFICATIONS:**

**Vast Expertise:** Offers over 20 years of broad and deep experience across various industries, demonstrating an exceptional understanding of diverse user landscapes and technological ecosystems.

**User-Centric Approach:** Proven ability to analyze user requirements and seamlessly integrate solutions, mitigating frustrations, redundancies, and inefficiencies within workflows.

**Academic Foundation:** Holds a solid educational background in economics, mathematics, and computer science, facilitating a unique blend of analytical thinking and technical proficiency.

Adaptability and Versatility: Proficient in multiple development environments, diverse technologies, and adaptive methodologies, ensuring agile problem-solving and effective project delivery.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Freelance, Software Engineer

JANUARY 2009 - Present

Interesting projects include: dynamic, parameter-driven 2D and 3D designs for makers; product comparison tool for building supplier to assist architects and builders to narrow a plethora of options for smart comparisons; extensive business process automation to streamline dataentry and improve reports; tool for displaying local food growers in a geographical region.

Wärtsilä. Sr. Software Engineer

AUGUST 2021 - NOVEMBER 2023

Optimized power plant management software and deployment to accelerate the transition towards a 100% renewable energy future. Improved user experience with additional features and bug fixes. Refactored OPC UA integration for stability and more than 10x throughput.

#### **TOOLS**

vim, emacs, git, docker, webpack, Adobe Photoshop, GIMP

# PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

javascript, HTML, CSS, node.js, Typescript, bash, go, Haskell, PHP, Clojure

# FRAMEWORKS / LIBRARIES

ReactJS, HapiJS, ExpressJS, Laravel, Symfony, Drupal, Magento

### **PRAGMA**

FP, DRY, Automation, Usability, RTFM, Section 508 Compliance, HIPAA Compliance

#### **BACKEND TECH**

docker, bash, nginx, Apache, MySQL, postgres, dynamodb, redis, GCP, AWS, Puppet

# **OPERATING SYSTEMS**

OSX, Linux, BSD variants, Windows 3.11-10

#### SPOKEN LANGUAGES

English, Conversational Spanish

#### Walmart Labs, Software Engineer III

MAY 2019 - JULY 2021

Interesting projects include: Automotive Care Center software, Point of Sale integration, legacy/nextgen interop and Product Activation Service.

Mobile application development with React Native. Systems automation. Backend service programming with golang.

## Storyblocks, Sr. Software Engineer

JANUARY 2018 - FEBRUARY 2019

Improved user experiences through updated interface designs, page speed increases and bug fixes. Improved developer experience and speed with automation, legacy code refactors and mentoring.

#### **Interactive Intelligence,** Durham, NC — Sr. Software Engineer

MAY 2015 - MARCH 2017

Multiple 3rd party systems integrations with business communication application, using combinations of nodeJS, ember, angular, reactJS and also Clojure with heavy Java interoperability. A heavy emphasis on reusable tool building and Amazon cloud technology.

**Questex,** Washington, DC — Sr. Web Developer

**APRIL 2014 - APRIL 2015** 

Reduced custom report serve time from 15+ minutes to realtime, using database call optimization, pre-caching and asynchronous data calls. Went on to make reports into dynamic and exportable dashboards, using AngularJS and d3js. Supported and improved existing system and troubleshot past data migration issues to recover previously missing data.

#### **SHRM**, Alexandria, VA — Web Developer

FEBRUARY 2011 - APRIL 2014

Application development, deploy and business automation using custom nodejs, Drupal, Magento, Django, iOS, puppet. High quality frontends paired with robust, automated backends, making for rapid, stable, incremental improvements.

# Rock Creek Strategic Marketing, Washington, DC — Developer

JANUARY 2010 - FEBRUARY 2011

Developed frontend features and automated backend infrastructure using PHP, JavaScript, CSS, mySQL, bash, sed, git and vim on a large scale, high profile Drupal platform as an on-site developer.

#### **INTERESTS**

Mathematics, Woodworking, Games, Puzzles, Martial Arts, Juggling, Speedcubing

## Blackbarn Media, Alexandria, VA - Sr. Developer

MARCH 2008 - JANUARY 2010

Performed development and integration tasks for projects using PHP, JavaScript, CSS, mySQL, Perl, bash, sed, awk, and vim for a development and hosting company. Worked directly with internal teams including designers, developers, and analysts to develop award winning web experiences. Worked directly with clients in commercial, non-profit, and government areas. Built and themed medium- to enterprise-level websites using Drupal. Provided front-end coding by turning design PSDs into functional frontends. Automated varied tasks including content migration, website building, and theming. Provided network troubleshooting and customer training.

# **PROJECTS**

# Open Source Contributor – Various

Where possible, contributed code for open-source projects including Wordpress, Drupal, and jQuery Mobile

Whitehouse.gov — Gamified Citizens Medal Nominee Selection Process

Used math, data migration, game application development and charm to reduce the candidate pool from over thirty thousand nominations down to the final 100 for the higher ups to choose from.

#### Whitehouse.gov — Video Indexing Applications

Built two different video applications for successful citizen engagement: one for indexing to particular questions/topics in the healthcare debate; another for video answers to twitter questions to the Press Secretary. Both web applications had to have easy to use administrative backends and also snappy, massively scalable frontends.

#### **EDUCATION**

**George Mason University,** Fairfax, VA — BS Economics, Math, Computer Science

Graduated 2007

Activities and Societies: Chess Club (founding member), Go Club, Robotics Club, Wing Chun